那个杀手是冲我来的
The assassin came for me.
每天钉死十个犹太人
10 Jews will be crucified
直到我抓到
every day until I have
那个想杀我的人为止
the man who tried to kill me.
爸爸
Papa.
他的名字 还有他的藏身地点
His name and where to find him.
要是我能找得到你 他们也会的
If I've found you, they will find you.
他的名字叫波阿斯
His name is Boaz.
- 哪都不安全  - 有个地方
- Nowhere is safe.  - There is somewhere.
那里的人能宽恕我的罪过
There are people who can forgive my sins.
我叫司提反
I'm Stephen.
- 闪开 孩子  - 不
- Move aside, boy.  - No.
亚拿尼亚 你的心里有什么
What's in your heart, Ananias,
叫你欺哄圣灵?
to make you lie to the Holy Spirit?
你和你的丈夫把房子卖掉的时候
When you and your husband sold your house,
有没有给自己私自留下一些?
did you keep anything back for yourselves?
可能是留了一点 那又有什么关系?
There might have been something, but what does that matter?
你欺哄人 不光是欺哄我们
You've lied, not just to us,
是欺哄神了
but to God.
本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
公元: 圣经续 第一季第5集
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调 影子
翻译: 飘飘行天下 小黄不小黄
翻译: 鸟生鱼汤 奥利奥 猫呗
校对: 飘飘行天下 影子
快跑!
Run!
他们害怕我
They're afraid of me.
发生在亚拿尼亚和撒非喇身上的事故与你无关
What happened to Ananias and Sapphira was not your doing.
那是神的意愿
It was the will of God.
那为何神要让营地上的人
Then why does God want the people of this camp
带着惧怕的目光看我呢?
to look on me with fear in their eyes?
那你见我的眼中有恐惧吗?
Do you see fear in mine?
他们心存信念
They have faith.
假以时日 他们会明白的
In time, they will understand.
这里本该是一片乐土
This is supposed to be a place of happiness.
如果每天在耶路撒冷都有同胞被钉死在十字架上
How can it be a joyful place when, every day,
这里又如何称得上是乐土呢?
more of our people are being crucified in Jerusalem?
人间苦难深重
There's so much pain and despair.
所以我儿子降临在这世界上
That's why my son came.
救大众于水火之中
to free us from it.
有波阿斯的消息了吗?
Any news of Boaz?
还没有 巡抚
Nothing, Governor.
今天在西区有个婚礼
There is a wedding today in the western quarter.
我敢肯定在这两家人中
I'm sure that between both families,
你能找到匡扶正义所需要牺牲的人
you will find the people justice demands.
抓10个女人...
Take 10 women...
送上十字架
and crucify them.
遵命 巡抚
Yes, Governor.
你有什么话要讲吗?
You have something to say?
你毫无怜悯之心吗?
Have you no mind for compassion?
丝毫没有
I have not.
对违抗命令的士兵 我的惩罚也不过如此
I do no more than I would to insubordinate soldiers.
是神惩罚了亚拿尼亚和撒非喇
Ananias and Sapphira were punished by God
因为他们欺哄了圣灵
for lying to t he Holy Spirit.
这件事引起了营地居民的极大关注
And this camp is focusing on that.
而这种... 恐惧击倒了我们所有人
And this... fear is paralyzing all of us.
然而我们要传递的应该 是爱与希望
But our message is one of love and hope.
那我们该怎么做?
So, what are we to do?
耶路撒冷里的人在受苦
There are people suffering in Jerusalem,
我们可以给他们提供容身之所
and we can offer them safety here.
与他们分享所有
Share what we have.
若非如此 我们和被神惩罚的那些人也没什么不同
If not, we're no different to those God has punished.
那我们就必须去耶路撒冷 不管有多危险
Then we must go to Jerusalem, no matter how dangerous it is.
都闪开!
Out of the way!
玛雅 这是他玛
Maya. This is Tamar.
她失去了所有亲人
She's lost everyone.
急需一个朋友
She really needs a friend.
咱们去找个地方让你住下吧?
Shall we go find a place for you to stay?
还有希望
There's hope.
他们给了我们一个名字... 波阿斯
They've given us a name... Boaz.
就快抓到了
They're closing in.
他们已经找到了他的未婚妻
They've already found his fiancee.
顺着她就能找到他
She could lead us right to him.
伊娃
Eva.
我们已经知道了 是波阿斯杀了罗马士兵
We know it was Boaz who murdered the Roman soldier.
你也知情
And so do you.
我帮不了你
I can't help you.
是帮整个耶路撒冷
It's Jerusalem that's asking for help
因为每天都有耶路撒冷人因他而死
because every day its people are being put to death
替他受过
in his absence.
如果他真的爱他的人民
If he truly loves his people,
那他就该准备好杀身成仁
then he will be ready to give up his life for theirs.
你是在浪费你的时间
You're wasting your time.
我求你了 伊娃
Then I beg you, Eva.
如果你知道点什么... 名字也好 地方也好 什么都行...
If you know something... a name or a place, anything...
你必须要告诉我
You must tell me.
抱歉 什么都没有
I'm sorry, there's nothing.
如果能救数百无辜犹太人的性命
It isn't a betrayal to save the lives
那就算不上是背叛
of hundreds of innocent Jews.
原谅我们擅自进来 但这些人都绝望了
Forgive our intrusion, but these people are desperate.
你能帮帮他们吗?
Can you help them?
即使有些人信仰不同?
Even those who do not share the belief?
你叫什么名字?
What is your name?
腓利
Philip.
他们怎么知道如何来这的?
How did they know to come here?
我带他们来的
I brought them.
我听了你讲的道
I heard you speak.
雅各给我施洗
And I was baptized by James.
而且不知怎的 我知道你会来
And somehow, I knew you'd come.
我们得把这些人弄出城
We need to get these people out of the city
越快越好
as quickly as possible.
怎么弄?
How?
罗马人就在街上随便抓人上十字架
Romans are out there looking for people to crucify.
带他们去营地 分散去
Take them to the camp. Go in small groups.
走不同的路线
Use different routes.
- 那里  - 是 长官
- There.  - Yes, sir.
腓利
Philip.
我能指望你把这些人组织好吗?
Can I trust you to organize these people?
没问题
You can.
现在!
Now!
是你干的 对吧?
It was you, wasn't it?
那个犹太婚礼... 你给他们通风报信了
The Jewish wedding... You tipped them off.
和巡抚夫人说话的时候注意点
Be careful how you speak to your governor's wife.
我倒想知道 要是自己的夫人试图阻挠他的命令
I wonder how he'd react if he knew she'd attempted
他会有什么反应
to sabotage his order.
只有我们两个人听到了这件事
You and I were the only ones who heard it.
我看得出你也讨厌那个命令
I saw your distaste for it.
不 我是一个士兵 我没有自己的看法
No, I'm a soldier. I don't have opinions.
正是因为有我这样的人在遵守命令 罗马才会繁荣昌盛
And Rome only thrives because men like me obey orders.
是啊 当然
Yes, of course.
抱着这种态度 你就能轻松
And how convenient that such an attitude absolves you
免除一切责任了
of any responsibility.
你以为会怎么样?
What did you think would happen?
我们在集市上抓了人充数
We took them from the market instead,
这都算在你头上
and that's on your head.
他们是更该死吗?
Were they any more or less deserving of death?
她有事情瞒着我们
She was holding something back.
我知道的
I know she was.
她会来找我们的
And she'll come.
相信我 她会来的
Trust me, she'll come.
我知道今天事态发展和计划的不太一样
I understand things didn't go entirely to plan today.
你觉得他们有没有可能知道你要去
Do you suppose it's possible that they knew you were coming,
因为有人警告过他们了?
that someone had alerted them?
我... 我觉得没有
I don't... I don't think so.
没... 没有迹象显示有人在我们来之前逃走
There... there was no sign that anyone had fled our arrival.
但是 嗯...
But, um...
今天在集市里没有女人?
There were no women at the market today?
男人们好像决定让女人躲到看不见的地方
The men seemed to have decided to keep women out of sight.
我相信你 司提反
I trust you, Stephen,
所以我想让你和腓利照顾营地
which is why I want you and Philip to look after the camp.
真的吗?
Really?
它壮大得太快了 还有那么多人前来投奔
It's growing so fast, and we have so many new converts.
彼得 我从十三岁开始
Peter, I've been reading and studying scripture
就在研读圣经
since I was 13.
整本书我都烂熟于心
I know entire pages by heart,
我可以用四种不同的语言说话 阅读 写字
and I can speak, read, and write in four different languages.
现在 神给我们每个人都有旨意
Now, God has a purpose for each of us.
你有你的 我有我的
You've got yours, and I have mine.
但是这不是神对我的旨意 我应该去传道
And that is not it. I'm meant to preach.
司提反
Stephen.
也许我可以让你好好利用你的学识
Maybe I can put your knowledge to good use.
伊娃?
Eva?
相信我 我不知道他在哪里
Believe me, I don't know where he is.
但他...
But he...
他说他要去一个地方
He said he was going to a place
那儿的人会原谅他的罪过
where people would forgive his sins.
跟我来
Come with me.
你把我带到这里来干什么?
Why have you brought me here?
我... 我知道的都告诉你了
I... I've told you what I know.
是的 但是...
Yes, but...
如果我的丈夫空手而归
If my husband returns empty-handed,
我就只能考虑
I will be forced to consider whether
你是不是故意误导我们
you deliberately misled us
还有你到底隐藏了什么真相
and then what truth you might conceal.
我已经把真相告诉你了
I've told you the truth.
那就希望他在那儿吧
Let's hope he's there, then.
走
Go.
神说 要有光 就有了光
God said, "let there be light," and there was light.
这个词是"神"?
This is the word for "God"?
非常好
Very good.
我们确信彼拉多想抓的人就在这里
We believe the man Pilate wants is here.
他的名字叫波阿斯
His name is Boaz.
你认识他...
You know him...
是吧?
don't you?
他曾经来寻求结盟
He once sought an alliance.
如果他在这里 你就必须要让他受到法律制裁
If he's here, you must allow him to face justice.
没错
Yes.
如果他在这里的话
If he's here.
要不要我提醒你 如果你不把他交出来
Need I remind you that if you fail to hand him over,
罗马的军队就会为他而来
Rome will come for him
并在须臾之内让这个营地灰飞烟灭
and wipe this camp from the earth in less than an hour.
如果罗马人觉得他在这里 我们早就死了
If the Romans thought he was here, we'd be dead already.
你自己尽管去找他好了
You are welcome to look for him yourself.
不要考验我的耐心!
Do not test me!
这里有成百无辜的民众
There are hundreds of innocent people here.
我为他们向神祈祷 你是个诚实可信的人
I pray to God for their sake you're truthful.
你... 你杀了一个人
You... you've taken a man's life.
你是个杀人犯
You're a killer.
你也是 我听说有一对夫妇被杀了
As are you. I hear a husband and wife were murdered.
你真的以为是我干的 你觉得我有这个能力?
Do you really think that was me, that I have that power?
只有神才能决定谁生谁死
Only God decides who lives and dies.
是神和罗马人
God and Romans.
我杀的那个人手里有过多少犹太人的人命?
How many Jewish lives have fallen to the man I killed?
这个理由不够 你没法为谋杀辩护!
That's not good enough. You cannot justify murder!
那你为什么不把我交给该亚法?
Then why didn't you give me up to Caiaphas?
因为只有神才能决定谁生谁死!
Because only God decides who lives and dies!
没人能强迫我决定一个人的命运!
I will not be compelled to decide a man's fate!
我可以收留你
I will harbor you.
但是我不能 也不会
But I cannot and will not
强迫你去自首
force you to surrender.
我们在这里的信念的基础
The foundation of what we believe in here
就是爱...
is love...
爱所有人
for all people.
我唯一能做的...
All I can do...
是宽恕你
is forgive you.
即便你知道罗马人一定会来找我
Even though you know Rome will surely come for me
并把这里夷为平地?
and destroy this place?
我信仰神
My faith is in God.
如果那是他的意愿 我接受
If that's his will, then so be it.
大祭司
High priest.
你是谁? 想干什么?
Who are you? What do you want?
我就是你要找的人
I'm the man you're looking for.
我是波阿斯
I'm Boaz.
为什么总有一些人
Why is it that some men
想方设法要摸老虎的尾巴呢?
are determined to pull the serpent's tail?
是活得不耐烦了?
Is it a death wish?
还是某种虚无缥缈的英雄主义?
Or is it some vague notion of heroism?
"我就是..." 这个 那个 或是其他什么样的人
"I'm the man who..." this, that, or the other.
英雄主义...
Heroism...
只存在于儿童故事里
It's for children's stories.
但是怪物...
But monsters...
怪物是真实存在的
Monsters are real.
而且无法被消灭
And they cannot be slayed.
招惹它们只会让其变本加厉 比之前更加凶残
Try, and they grow another head that bites back twice as hard.
那么 应该做的是... 安抚它们
So, what to do... Placate them,
取悦它们 满足它们 直到它们又胖又懒
flatter them, feed them until they're fat and indolent,
忘记了自己是怪物
and forget that they're monsters.
假以时日
And in time,
它们就会离开
they move on.
你比我更瞧不起彼拉多
You despise Pilate more than I do.
而且我知道
And I know that deep down,
在你内心深处 你巴不得
you wish with all your heart
我能成功杀死他
that I'd succeeded in killing him.
他在这儿 也许你想要见见他
He's here, if you want to see him.
好让他死之前知道我背叛了他?
So that he'll die knowing that I betrayed him?
不管你信不信 他并不知情
For what it's worth, he didn't.
他不是因为你被抓到的
He wasn't found through you.
他是自首的
He surrendered.
你好像挺喜欢她的
You seem taken with her.
我记得那是什么感觉
I remember how it feels.
我在她这个年纪失去了妈妈
I was about her age when my mother died,
我再也不想又一次被人抛下
and I didn't ever want to be left alone again.
今天你把她照顾得非常好
You've been wonderful with her today.
但你决不能认为她是你的责任
But you mustn't think she's your responsibility.
但我理解她的感受
But I know how it feels.
我知道她的需求
I know what she needs.
那么你认为你能给她那一切吗?
And do you think you can give that to her?
总要有人去做 为何不能是我?
Somebody should. Why not me?
因为你自己都还只是个孩子呢 玛雅
Because you're still a child yourself, Maya.
也许就是这样她才想要我陪着
Maybe that's why she wants me around.
因为我跟她很像
Because I'm like her.
我不是成年人
I'm not an adult.
而是朋友
I'm a friend.
我们终于抓到了波阿斯
We have Boaz, finally.
噢
Oh.
谢谢你来告诉我
Thank you for coming to me.
你这样会有风险吧
It was a risk.
不会 一切终于可以恢复原样了
No. Anything to at last get back to normality.
原样?
Normality?
是什么意思?
What is that?
杀人犯会受到应有的惩罚
The murderer will be punished for his crime,
报复行为也结束了
and the reprisals ended.
而且还会恢复以前那种自然的平衡
And the natural balance of things will be restored.
是这个意思吗?
Is that it?
再说一遍?
I'm sorry?
你似乎觉得在波阿斯这事发生前
You seem to think that before Boaz,
一切都是理所应当的样子
everything was as it should be.
以前很稳定啊
Well, there was stability.
我知道我们的民族之间有差异 但是...
I know our nations have their differences, but...
我们生活在罗马暴政的铁蹄之下...
We live under the heel of Roman tyranny...
占领军耗尽了我们的资源
an occupying army that drains us of resources
对我们肆意欺凌杀害
and doles out murder on a mass scale.
把我们变成奴隶
We are enslaved.
但你现在是以自由之身站在我面前 不是吗?
But you stand here freely with me now, don't you?
这不过是因为你允许我这样做
Only because you allow me to.
而作为交换
And in return,
你要我对你表示感激
you expect me to play the role of the grateful subject
因为你也是他们的一员... 一个罗马人
because you are one of them... a Roman.
你们才是问题所在
You are the problem.
管好你的嘴巴 小贱人!
Bite your tongue, little snake!
不要假装很了解我
Don't presume to know me.
你会为此付出不菲的代价
That might prove a costly error.
这个
There.
看到了吗?
You see?
至少我们了解自己处在什么样的地位
At least we know where we stand.
你怎么找到他的?
How did you find him?
知识就是力量
Knowledge can be as effective as force.
你就是凶手 证明给我看
You are the murderer. Prove it.
告诉我你割的哪里
Show me where you struck.
不
No.
过来 在我身上
Here. On me.
就这样 近一点
That's it. Closer.
现在可以了
Now show me.
至少他死得很快
At least he died quickly.
然而你...
Whereas you will die...
会在很多天以后 才慢慢 慢慢死去
very slowly over many, many days
以儆效尤
as an example for all to see.
离得这么近感觉如何?
How does it feel to get this close?
诱人犯罪
Tempting.
你会为自己的所作所为 饱尝无尽的痛苦滋味
There will be no end to your pain for what you did.
不仅波阿斯比我想要的早死了一个星期
Not only is Boaz dead one week sooner than I'd like him to be,
你还让杀他之人逃之夭夭
you somehow have contrived to allow his killer to escape.
作何解释!
Explain yourself!
恕我无能
It was my failing.
我本该料想到有人会杀他灭口
I should have anticipated an attempt to stop him talking.
我本该在他射箭的屋顶安设人手
I should have placed men on the rooftops where he struck.
我的失误让他得以轻易逃脱
Failure to do so gave him an easy escape.
这个让人厌烦的城市终于惹恼你了吗?
Is this cloying city finally getting under your skin?
犯一个错可以饶过
A single mistake could be forgiven,
但你犯得不只一个错吧?
but this isn't a single mistake, is it?
我任凭你发落
I accept whatever punishment pleases you.
从我的视线里消失
Get out of my sight.
他是谁?
Who was he?
一个信仰坚定的人
A man of great conviction,
只可惜误入歧途
but tragically misguided.
让我们单独呆会
Leave us.
# 神阿 求你救我 #
# Save me, o God #
# 因为众水要淹没我 #
# for the waters are come into my soul #
# 我陷在深淤泥中 没有立脚之地 #
# I sink in deep mire where there is no standing #
# 我到了深水中 #
# I am come into deep waters #
# 大水漫过我身 #
# where the floods overflow me #
# 我因呼求困乏 #
# I am weary of my crying #
# 喉咙发干 #
# my throat is dried #
# 我因等候神 眼睛失明 #
# my eyes fail while I wait for my God #
# 无故恨我的 #
# they that hate me without a cause #
# 比我头发还多 #
# are more than the hairs on my head #
请不要论断眼前之人
Do not judge this man displayed here.
那是神的职责
That's for God to do.
我们只能饶恕他的过犯
All we can do is forgive him,
如同饶恕众人的过犯
as we must forgive all people,
并向众人示爱
and show love to all men.
只有彼时我们才能在我们的主 耶稣基督
Only then will we find salvation when our Lord, Jesus Christ,
降临耶路撒冷 建立起一个新的神之国度时
returns to establish a new kingdom of God
获得拯救
in Jerusalem.
带走他
Take him.
要追他回来吗?
Shall I stop him?
不用
No.
让他去通风报信
Let him tell the others.
他们自然会来搭救朋友
They'll come for their friend.
我们只需静候在此
And we will be waiting.
好吧 没事
All right. All right.
这是干什么? 我们什么也没做
What is this? We haven't done anything.
是还没有 但你们会的
No. But you will.
逮捕他们!
Arrest them!
彼得 你还好吧?
Peter. Are you all right?
给我去那边!
Get out of here!
你也是!
You too!
彼得
Peter.
这可不妙
This isn't good.
他们在等着我们上门
They were waiting for us.
我们将会遭受苦难
Something awful is going to befall us.
但这也将是神迹的开始
But it will mark the beginning of something wonderful.
谢谢你结束他的痛苦
Thank you for making it swift.
这不是出于仁慈
It was not done out of kindness.
而是为了拯救他人 波阿斯知道这点
It was to save lives. Boaz knew that.
可以牺牲他
He was expendable.
你需要人取代他
You'll need to replace him.
我现在也参与进来了
I'm in this now, too.
教导我 如同你教导波阿斯一样
Teach me, like you taught Boaz.
教我如何杀人
Show me how to kill.
我的朋友... 时机到了
My friends... it's time.
他要带我们去哪里?
Where is he taking us?
去神殿
To the temple.
我们的民族已被毒害 从仇恨中回头吧
Our nation is poisoned. Turn away from hate.
从暴力中回头吧
Turn away from violence.
耶稣是世上的光
Jesus is the light of the world.
- 阿门!  - 敞开心胸
- Amen!  - Open your hearts.
聆听对众生希望与爱的福音
Hear our message of hope and love for all people.
加入我们
Come.
耶稣是位好牧人
Jesus is the good Shepherd.
倘若人们知道
People would not act this way
我主耶稣基督的国 将降临耶路撒冷
if they knew the kingdom of our Lord, Jesus Christ,
便不会如此相待
is coming to Jerusalem.
他是复活...
He is the resurrection...
- 他 还有他 把他们带走!  - 是生命!
- Him. Him. Take them!  - And the life!
我知道问你也是徒劳
I suppose it's thankless to ask,
但我还是很想知道你是如何越狱的
but I'd very much like to know how you escaped your cell.
那么我只能假设
Then I can only assume
你们懂一点撬锁
that you have some experience of lock-picking,
大多数通晓事理的人都会把这种本事
a skill which most reasonable people
与犯罪联系在一起
would associate with criminality.
很好
Very well.
你们被指控一直
You are accused of continuing
奉假先知的名教训人
to teach the name of a false prophet.
你们藐视神殿 阴谋把这座城里
You defy the temple and conspire to lead
迷失的灵魂引入迷途
the lost souls of this city astray.
你对此作何解释?
What have you to say to this?
回答我!
Answer me!
出于对犹太公会博学多识的长老们的尊重
Out of respect for the learned elders of the Sanhedrin,
我们无意辩解我们的信仰
we will not seek to defend our beliefs.
我们只知道其为真
We only know them to be true.
而真理无需辩解 澄清
There can be no defense or clarification
又或是开脱... 真理即是真理
or mitigation of the truth... It simply is.
那何谓你的真理?
And what is the truth?
那便是神将耶稣从死里复活
That God raised Jesus from the dead
坐在他的右边 叫他作君主 作救主
to sit at his right hand as prince and savior.
正是他的圣灵替我们打开枷锁
And it was his Spirit that freed us from your chains.
你可知说出如此僭妄之语
You are aware that saying such things
根据律法将把你当假先知定罪
condemns you as false prophets, according to the law.
只会有一种结果
There is only one outcome.
那就是将你们以乱石砸死
You are to be put to death by stones.
就这么几句话...
So few words spoken...
就要处死这么多人
for so many lives to be clipped.
迦玛列拉比
Rabbi Gamaliel,
你是发现我们在适用的法律有什么错吗?
do you find fault in our application of the law?
不不不 应该不是
No, no, no, probably not.
但是作为犹太公会的主席
But as president of the Sanhedrin,
我有义务去干涉
I'm obligated to poke a finger into matters
引起我关注的事情
that pique my interest.
理所当然 但这事还有什么好说的?
Of course, but what more is there to say?
他们已被判有罪...
They've been found guilty of...
是的 是的 这真叫人心里不安
Yes, yes, yes, yes. It's all very upsetting.
但是我很好奇 难道你就没想起
But I wonder, do you not recall
你自己年少时的那份热情
the enthusiasms of your own youth
并为之神往吗?
and being carried away by them?
大家对您的智慧赞赏有加 但是...
Your wisdom is highly valued and recognized by all, but...
但是我现在该坐回去了 是吗?
But I should sit down now, should I?
不 不 我不能
No, no, I cannot.
为了你我 我的良心刺痛了我
My conscience pricks at me for us both.
任凭他们去吧
Let these men alone.
他们并不是危险分子
They are not dangerous.
假如他们所言虚假 那就不会有任何事发生
If what they claim is false, then nothing will come of it.
假以时日 他们也就四散了
And in time, they will simply fade away.
但假如所言为实 而你们将之毁灭
But if it is true and you destroy them,
恐怕你们自己
you will find yourselves
倒是攻击神了
in opposition to God.
迦玛列所言甚是
Having considered the wisdom of Gamaliel,
同意改变你们的判决
it is agreed that the sentence shall be commuted.
但是你们仍会被公开处以鞭刑
But you're to be taken to a public place and flogged
好让你们的罪行公诸于众!
so that everyone may know your guilt!
你若不听从耶和华 你神的话
If you do not obey the Lord, your God,
不谨守遵行他的一切诫命律例
and do not carefully follow all his commands and decrees,
你在城里必咒受诅 在田间也必咒受诅
you will be cursed in the city and cursed in the country.
你身所生的 地所产的
The fruit of your womb will be cursed.
以及牛犊 羊羔
The crops of your land, the calves of your herds,
都必受咒诅
the lambs of your flocks.
你出也受咒诅 入也受咒诅
You will be cursed when you come in and cursed when you go out.
他必在你手里所办的一切事上
The Lord will send on you
使咒诅 扰乱 责罚临到你
curses, confusion, and rebuke in everything you put your hand to
直到你被毁灭 速速地灭亡
until you are destroyed and come to sudden ruin
因为你行恶离弃他
because of the evil you have done in forsaking him.
我们都知道总要付出一点牺牲
We all knew we'd have to make sacrifices.
这是耶稣告诉我们的 司提反
That's what Jesus told us, Stephen.
不是这样的牺牲
Not like this.
我们能不能回家...
Shall we go home...
去加利利吗?
To Galilee?
你是说去那生活吗?
You mean to live?
为什么不呢?
Why not?
营地建好了 正在发展壮大
The camp's set up. It's growing.
你不需要再待在这了
You don't need to be here anymore.
这就是你想要的吗?
Is that what you want?
是的
Yes.
但是你做不到 是吗?
But you can't do it, can you?
你在家的时候...
When you're at home...
捕鱼 卖鱼
you catch fish, you sell them.
清扫船只
You clean a boat.
我可以做 谁都可以做
I can do that. Anyone can.
但是在这不一样
But it's different here.
你与众不同
You're different.
甚至你的名字都与众不同
Even your name's different.
你是彼得 独一无二
You're Peter. No one else can be.
所以我才要回家
And that's why I'm going home.
什么时候走?
When?
明天
Tomorrow.
他玛认定我是唯一一个
Tamar's decided that I'm the only one
能护她周全的人 而且...
that can keep her safe, and...
在这儿我保护不了她
and I can't do that here.
我会想你的
I'm going to miss you
你不会知道我有多想你
more than you will ever know.
我们要根据我们的法律来管理自己
We must govern ourselves according to our law
这样这个城市以及它的人民
so that this city and its people
将不再受到罗马法律的制裁
are never again subjected to Roman justice.
这样好倒是好
That's all well and good.
但是依我所见
But as far as I understand it,
这个波阿斯自愿被捕
this Boaz surrendered of his own accord.
是这些人宣称遵守摩西律法吗?
Are these the men that claim to keep the law of Moses?
你们... 你们受了天使所传的律法
You... you who have received the law through angels
竟不遵守!
but have not obeyed it!
你们都跟我们的祖先一样
You're all just like our ancestors.
哪一个先知 不是他们逼迫呢?!
Was there ever a prophet they didn't persecute?!
够了!
Enough!
为什么要这么做?
What is the cause of this?
义者受到了不公的处罚
The unjust punishment of righteous men.
小心你的措辞
Hush your tongue.
那是在神的眼下 神的殿里执行的判决
The sentence was levied under the eyes of God in his house.
哦 你是说这个神殿?
Oh, you mean this temple?
你真相信 能创造万物的神
Do you really believe that God would confine himself
会把自己限制在一所人造的屋子里吗?
to a house built by men, when he made all of creation?!
哦 你说话小心一点 你可是一个人在这
Oh, you be careful. You're alone in here.
难道耶稣没有在
And didn't Jesus say,
你将他处死而他又复活前说过
"I will tear down this temple and rebuild it in three days"
"我能拆毁神的殿 三日内又建造起来"吗?!
before he rose from the death you condemned him to?!
让他安静 让他闭嘴
Silence him. Shut him up.
看啊 和我一起看!
Look. Look here with me!
我看见天开了 基督站在神的右边
I see the heavens open and Christ standing at the right hand of God!
杀了这个亵渎神灵的人! 杀了他!
Kill the blasphemer! Kill him!
求主耶稣接收我的灵魂
Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.
不要将这罪归于他们
Do not hold this sin against them.
这是权利与信仰的对抗
It's power versus faith.
烧了它
Burn it.
就在这场史诗般的对决
In one epic showdown.
让我们见证新生的火焰烧得愈加璀璨
Let's see new fire burns brightest.